בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is דף ו, Daf Vav,
and we're always a little bit, oh I got you a little
bit ahead. Let's see how we can do with that. So we
pick up on the middle of דף ו עמוד א Daf Vav
Amud Aleph and it's really right in the middle,
תנן Tnan which is one, two, three, four, five, seven lines from
the bottom by the asterisks, middle of the line. So just to
remind you we're dealing with a debate of בר פדא Bar Pada
and רב מתנא. Rav Masna. רב מתנא Rav Masna says that a
נזירות Nezirus of thirty days means thirty days, and however because it's
clear from a series of משניות Mishnayos that we quoted that you
can bring your קרבן Korban on day thirty, he has to modify
it by saying that what it really means, that it's thirty days
but there's a principle of מקצת היום ככולו. Miktzas Hayom Kekulo. A
partial day is considered like the complete day. And as I said
to people you most are familiar with this from אבילות, Aveilus, that
the אבל Avel gets up on the seventh day in the morning,
does not do a seventh full day, so here too there's that
principle and which is why the משנה Mishnah not only tells you
you can bring your קרבנות Korbanos on day thirty even though it's
supposed to be thirty days but says that לכתחילה Lechatchila it wants
you to bring it on day thirty-one, wait till the full thirty
days are out. Why there's that לכתחילה Lechatchila there and not by
אבילות, Aveilus, that might become a little bit clear in a minute.
בר פדא Bar Pada on the other hand says no, that when
it says נזירות Nezirus of thirty days it doesn't mean in principle
thirty days it means in principle twenty-nine, but it's twenty-nine full days,
I don't buy into this idea of מקצת היום ככולו. Miktzas Hayom
Kekulo. And therefore you wind
up ipso facto you wind up bringing it on day thirty, but
in principle it's twenty-nine but twenty-nine full days, no principle of מקצת
היום. Miktzas Hayom. Why therefore לכתחילה Lechatchila you should wait till day
thirty-one is less clear, it's to account for certain cases where maybe
a person explicitly said thirty days or something of that nature. So
why that's a לכתחילה Lechatchila is less clear, but his basic principle
is twenty-nine days, full days, no מקצת היום, Miktzas Hayom, and that's
why you wind up bringing it on day thirty. So two very
different models of understanding of why you bring it on day thirty.
Rabbi Dov was speaking to me afterwards like what is this idea
that a half a day counts as a whole day? Like when
do we say that? So there are two things to think about.
First of all there are times in הלכה Halacha for example we
say רובו ככולו. Rubo Kekulo. If you do the majority it's like
you did the whole thing. Classic common example not necessarily that people
experience on a regular basis but classic common example would be שחיטה,
Shechita, you don't have to sever both the trachea and the esophagus
fully, it's enough to cut the majority of it.
Or maybe if you want to think about another example which is
maybe a little more relevant, when you're like enclosing an area for
a עירוב, Eiruv, if the majority is let's say there's not any
huge gaps but you don't have to have a consistent wall throughout
the entire side, there can be small gaps as long as the
majority is walled off.
And again we're not doing הלכות עירוב Hilchos Eiruv right now. So
there are times where we say that as long as you achieve
the majority of something it's like you achieved it. But that's normally
when the goal is to achieve a particular state, right? You need
it to be considered severed, you need it to be considered walled
off. If it's to do a particular action you wouldn't say, well
what would be an example, as I did the majority of some
מצוה, Mitzvah, I don't know, I ate
the
majority of a כזית, Kezayis, I דאוון Daven the majority of a
שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, whatever, okay anyway we wouldn't say it right?
So here if you're supposed to do an X number of days
to
say well anyway it's not even a majority, it's even a little
bit, the guy gets up from אבילות Aveilus in the morning. So
it's not really the מקצת היום ככולו Miktzas Hayom Kekulo idea. A
better way of thinking about it is that we normally say this
in things that are a duration of like a week or a
month or like a period of time, right? And if you think
about it I say well did I complete a week? Did I
complete a month? So there you could say well maybe as soon
as you enter into the last day of that of that process,
since we're not counting, if we said did you have seven days,
you didn't have seven days you had six and a half days,
you had twenty-nine and a half days, but I want to know
did I have thirty days, I want to know did I do
a month. A month is defined by thirty days but conceptually it's
about a month. So since conceptually we focus on the month we
might want to say that once you began the thirtieth day that's
already like you've done the month. So that's like a way of
thinking about when we say מקצת היום ככולו Miktzas Hayom Kekulo and
it really is more limited to cases like this where we focus
on a sort of on a unit, on a unit that's consists
of a duration of a number of things but we focus on
the unit and not on the number. Okay so that is a
very important Halachic principle, that's what רב מתנא Rav Masna says, in
theory it's thirty days or in theory it's a month but going
into the thirtieth day is enough and בר פדא Bar Pada says
no no no it's twenty-nine, twenty-nine complete days. So now let's take
a look as the גמרא Gemara continues this. תנן. Tnan. So now
again we are like seven lines from the bottom on
ו עמוד א. Vav Amud Aleph. אם גילח יום ששים חסר אחד
יצא שיום שלשים עולה לו מן המנין. Im Gilach Yom Shishim Chasar
Echad Yatza Sheyom Shloshim Oleh Lo Min Haminyan. So this is going
back to the case we dealt with
yesterday thankfully. Okay so this says that somebody basically has a double
נזירות, nezirut, one נזירות nezirut following another. So as we pointed out,
לכתחילה lechatchila person is supposed to do it on day 31, right?
For whatever reason we said. But if בדיעבד bedieved he went ahead
and did it on day 30, okay, he's יוצא. yotze. Fine. Then
when does he bring the second one? So the second one it
said ideally it should be on... oh, I'm up here. Okay. The
second one we said ideally should be on day 60. Why? Because
if he brought his קרבן korban on day 30, day 30 becomes
day 1. Oh, now I see what I did. Day 30 becomes
day 1, so day 60, right? It's just subtract 29. So day
60 becomes day 31, and that's consistent with the idea that we
said לכתחילה lechatchila you do it on day 31. So this guy,
he should have done it on day 31. He did it at
day 30, which also works, as we said, מקצת היום ככולו, miktzat
hayom kekulo, whatever the principle is. Now the משנה mishna had said
yesterday, fine, but still לכתחילה lechatchila do this on day 60, which
is this one's day 31, right? Everybody see how that math works?
But it says if בדיעבד bedieved you did this on day 59,
which then becomes this this day 30, that's also good. Same point:
לכתחילה lechatchila do it on day 31, בדיעבד bedieved you do it
on day 30, it also works. Okay, so that's what the משנה
mishna said. Okay, אם גילח יום ששים חסר אחד יצא שיום שלשים
עולה לו מן המנין. Im gilach yom shishim chaser echad yatza sheyom
shloshim oleh lo min haminyan. Because ultimately this day 30 counts both
ways. This is the principle. It ended this this period and it
began the next period, עולה לכאן ולכאן. oleh lakan ulakan. Okay, and
then we said like part of the חידוש chidush of מקצת היום
ככולו miktzat hayom kekulo is you could say day 30 was like
the full day 30 of the previous count and like the beginning
day 1 of the following count. That's we said that already yesterday.
בשלמא
לרב מתנא ניחא. Bishlama leRav Matna nicha. According to רב מתנא Rav
Matna this makes sense. You know, we said that מקצת היום ככולו,
miktzat hayom kekulo, day 30 finished one count, began the next count,
you can say it לכאן ולכאן. lakan ulakan. אלא לבר פדא למה
לי? Ela leBar Pada lama li? According to בר פדא, Bar Pada,
what's the חידוש? chidush? המשלשים חסר אחד. Hamashloshim chaser echad. There's no
חידוש chidush of עולה לכאן ולכאן oleh lakan ulakan because בר פדא
Bar Pada says anyway in principle it's 29 days, and therefore of
course day 30 works. Because day 30, right? You had 29 full
days, right? And then of course this is going to work. Because
if you say like like רב מתנא, Rav Matna, there's a חידוש.
chidush. You really need 30 days and the חידוש chidush is this
counts as a full day 30 for the past and as a
beginning for the for the coming one. So that this also, and
if you did it in the middle of this day 30 it
also works. So you're doing like a lot of מקצת היום ככולו's,
miktzat hayom kekulo right? Here you did a מקצת היום ככולו miktzat
hayom kekulo to count for the past and to use this day
to count for the future. Counting the second count and this you
did a מקצת היום ככולו. miktzat hayom kekulo. But according to בר
פדא, Bar Pada, there's no big חידוש. chidush. This is after day
29, and then this is after day 29. So it's not so
interesting that case. Let's just see the answer. גמרא Gemara gives the
similar answer that we gave yesterday. אמר לך אנא
נמי מהתם סמכי. Amar lach ana nami mehatam samchi. That's also where
I get it from. Huh? What does that mean? So what he
says it means is, here's what here's the way the ר"ן Ran
explains. בר פדא Bar Pada says, "I," right? The question is why
are you allowed to double count this? Everybody with me? Why are
you allowed to double count this day 30? If it's based on
מקצת היום ככולו, miktzat hayom kekulo, that's like a conceptually hard idea.
You're telling me it's like even though you bring the קרבן korban
in the middle of day 30, it's like it was already a
full day 30 for the first count number one. But if it's
a full day 30 for first count number one, it is conceptually
hard to understand how it can also begin to be the beginning
of the following count. So בר פדא Bar Pada says when the
משנה mishna says עולה... oleh... that this day is עולה לכאן ולכאן,
oleh lakan ulakan, right?
He says what I interpret that to mean is... Is that the
language used by the way? By the way, what is that, the
גמרא's Gemara language?
Yeah, it is, עולה לכאן ולכאן. oleh lakan ulakan. When it says
that, he says what I say that means is, you know why
day 30 can count for the beginning of the next count? Because
it really wasn't part of the previous count, which is funny to
read into the words עולה לכאן ולכאן. oleh lakan ulakan. עולה לכאן
ולכאן oleh lakan ulakan sounds like you're counting it in two directions.
But he says I am choosing to read that the reason this
works is because you don't need it for the previous count. The
reason this works for the coming count is because it was really
only 29 days. Okay? So he's saying that to me is that's
where I get my idea from. I could not get my head
around saying that this day gets to get double counted. Right? Everybody
get how this day looks like it's being double counted? Right? If
you only have 59 days and you're supposed to do two units
of 30, think about it this way. The total's 59 days, two
units of 30, the only way you're going to get that is
if you overlap the middle day, right? Because two units of 30
equals 60. So he says I cannot get my head around how
you can count that day twice. So I say that the point
of to that משנה Mishna. *mishna*, it's to tell you that this
day gets to count because you really only need 29 days. Yes.
Wait, so this is the בר פדא Bar Padda, *Bar Pada* question
because in our משנה Mishna *mishna* there is an overlap, it's לכאן
ולכאן *l'kan ul'kan*. Right. But for... for בר פדא Bar Padda *Bar
Pada*, when you finish your first of the two sequential נזירות Nazirus.
*neziruyot*, do you have to bring a קרבן Korban. *korban* after the
first one and then go into the second one?
Yeah, that's why I keep on having my little animal here. You
have to. Everybody says that. The only way you start the next
one is by bringing a קרבן Korban.
*korban*. You always have to bring, even if it's an overlapping, intersecting,
overlapping day?
Yeah, that's part of the point. Right? So the second part of
the משנה Mishna. *mishna* says that in the end, you brought your
first one on day
29, on day 30, day 30... this is a duration of 30
days.
Okay, this is a duration of 30 days. Right? So here's the
problem, right? It says you brought your first קרבן Korban.
*korban* here, and
your second קרבן Korban *korban* here, right? And you're יוצא *yotze*. But
the point is, how could you be יוצא *yotze* two units, two
durations of 30, it's only 59 days? Oh, because that middle day
gets to double count. Okay, so if, so what רב מתנה *Rav
Masna*... but you're bringing your קרבן Korban *korban*. So what רב מתנה
*Rav Masna* says is, yeah, that's the חידוש chiddush. המקצת היום ככולו
*chiddush hamiktzat hayom k'kulo*, you get to bring your קרבן Korban, *korban*,
count for the previous one and count for the next one. And
בר פדא Bar Padda *Bar Pada* says that doesn't make any sense.
What it really means is that it was only about 29 days.
Is there ever even a fraction of a second in which you're
not a נזיר Nazir *nazir* when you're doing...
no, no, no. As soon as the first נזירות nezirut *nezirus* ends,
I mean, conceptually, logically, one ends and the next begins, but in
real time, there's no gap of space.
Oh, so you stand on... so this is the ר"ן *Ran*? Is
this the ר"ן *Ran* on this?
This is the... oh, I'm... you're right, it's תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*. I
got confused. I started calling תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* the ר"ן *Ran*. You
know why I started calling תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* the ר"ן *Ran*? Not
only because we're at the top of the page, yes, but not
only that, it's because תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* here, if you've been wondering
why are there these huge תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos*...
Yeah, I was wondering.
Let me tell you why there are these huge תוספות *Tosfos*, because
תוספות *Tosfos* here takes up the mantle of the ר"ן *Ran* in
נדרים *Nedarim*. I mean, I'm not saying that he was taking up
the mantle because he had gone to take, but the point is,
80 percent of these תוספות *Tosfos* or maybe more for this דף
Daf, *daf* is just commentary. It's not like asking questions and getting
answers. It's not the dialectic. He's really doing a lot of the
work that the ר"ן *Ran* did. Again, because the רש"י *Rashi* isn't
really רש"י *Rashi*. So a lot of this תוספות *Tosfos* is really
running commentary. Okay, so let's take a look. It says like this:
Okay, yes.
So do you have to decide either one way or the other,
or it can be either way?
Well, it can't be either way, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* often
ends and does not פסקן *pasken* a debate. It's keeping both opinions
alive, right? I mean, we don't get to say I like... I
mean, you know, if we were to be פסקן *paskening* this הלכה
Halacha *halacha*, you'd have to ask which is the one we פסקן
*pasken* like, right? But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't always, as I
pointed out, you know, Michael often asks, so how do we פסקן
*pasken*? So the point is, you know, it's a mistake to think
that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s primary goal is to come to a
הלכתית *halachic* conclusion. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is trying to explore the
opinion. It is not... sometimes it'll פסקן *pasken*, you know. All right.
So now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says: What if somebody's not doing consecutive, but takes on a
60-day נזירות nezirut.
*nezirus*? Right, then they wait till the 60 full days. Well, actually
we're going to get a case like that in a minute. So
let's hold on. Okay. But if they say 60 explicitly, then even
בר פדא Bar Padda. *Bar Pada* would say you have to wait
till day 61, right? Because בר פדא Bar Padda *Bar Pada* only
says that a סתם נזירות stam nezirut *stam nezirus* is 29. But
remember the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said yesterday, you know, or we said
that if you say 30 days, בר פדא Bar Padda *Bar Pada*
doesn't believe in מקצת היום ככולו Miktzas Hayom Kekulo, *miktzat hayom k'kulo*,
so you have to wait till day 31. The only reason this
works is because you didn't say an amount, so we just interpret
נזיר Nazir *nazir* to be 29 days.
But if he said, I take on a double נזירות nezirut. *nezirus*?
Yeah, if you use that phrase, I don't know if that... okay,
but we'd probably translate that as 58 days for him, and then
he'd bring it on day 59. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this: תנן Tnan: *Tnan*: מי שאמר Mi she'amar, הריני
נזיר hareini nazir *mi she'amar hareni nazir*, somebody says I'll be a
נזיר Nazir, *nazir*, נטמא יום שלשים *nitma yom shloshim*, סותר את הכל
soter et hakol. *soter et hakol*. And now we're going to get
a little insight into why לכתחילה *l'chatchila* you should wait to day
31. He said I'm a נזיר nazir *nazir*. Now we've just said
you can bring your קרבן Korban, *korban* on day 30. But let's
say after you brought your קרבן Korban *korban* on day 30, you
became טמא Tamei, *tamei*. Now, here's the irony. After you bring your
קרבן korban, *korban* on day 30, you can drink wine. You can
go get a haircut. But those are seen to be as like
a prohibition of being a נזיר nazir, *nazir*. But becoming טמא tamei,
*tamei* is a... not just a violation, but it like it counteracts,
it's, you know, what's the word I'm looking for?
It's like almost defiling your נזירות nezirut *nezirus*. And therefore, that's when
you come טמא tamei, *tamei* you have to start the whole thing
again. If you drink wine, you don't start it again. If you
get a haircut, you don't start it again. So here is the
thing: You bring your קרבן korban, *korban* on day 30, you're going
to go get wine, go get a haircut, but if you become
טמא tamei, *tamei*, then that says that ultimately your נזירות nezirut. *nezirus*
was undermined and you have to start the whole thing, because here's
the logic: since we say that מקצת היום ככולו Miktzas Hayom Kekulo.
*miktzat hayom k'kulo*, to some degree what we're saying is sort of
like רובו ככולו *rubo k'kulo*, what I said before... is like it
works because it's like you did the whole 30th day. But if
we then take a step back and say, one minute, in the
real 30th day as it was then lived out afterwards, you became
טמא, tamei. and we have to be able to step back and
say it's like we can't say it's like you did full 30
days as a נזיר Nazir if what happened during the end of
that day 30 was something that counteracts the whole idea of נזירות.
nezirut. Okay, so again, if you got a haircut, if you got
if you drank wine, that's not a problem. That doesn't counteract the
idea. And bottom line is you brought your קרבן. korban? You did
end it in the middle of the day. But if at the
end of the day something fundamentally counteracts that idea, then we cannot
say that it's like by the beginning of the day everything was
because something that you know that that little day was conceptually supposed
to include the end of the day, and in the real end
of the day there was something that counteracted it. Let me give
you another example about this, which is where else I think mentions
מקצת היום ככולו, Miktzas Hayom Kekulo, and that is in the Torah's
case of a of a זבה. Zava. A נידה, Niddah, right in
the Torah is a woman who after on the from the onset
of her menstrual cycle, so the evening following day 7 of the
onset brings a קרבן. korban That's not מקצת היום ככולו. Miktzas Hayom
Kekulo, It's like seven full days from the onset and then the
evening brings a קרבן. korban, But if a woman bleeds not during
her menstrual period, three days consecutively, then she has to count seven
days of non-bleeding. And that seven days, day seven, actually she does
not in principle have to wait till the end of day seven,
she can go ahead and go to the מקוה Mikvah on day
seven, okay.
Now the question is and is what were to happen if she
went to the מקוה Mikvah on day seven, had sex with her
husband, it's still day seven, and then she bled before nightfall. Okay,
so because remember it has to be seven consecutive non-bleeding days. So
the הלכה Halacha would be then it all gets undermined and she
was always a זבה Zava and the going to the מקוה Mikvah
didn't count and she needs a you know a new a new
period of seven days. Which is why why the הלכה halacha? is
that if a woman goes to the מקוה Mikvah on day seven,
she still has to wait to have sex with her husband until
the night, because you don't want that scenario to happen, right, or
maybe you even wait to go to the מקוה Mikvah till the
night because you don't want that scenario to happen. And that's exactly
analogous here. Why do they wait till day 31, whatever happened to
מקצת היום ככולו, miktzat hayom kekulo, because if you go on bring
the קרבן korban. on day 30 and you go and get a
haircut and you go and get and and you drink wine and
then you became טמא, tamei then retroactively you were always a נזיר
nazir, and you were violating it as of on that rest of
that day. So therefore best idea bring the קרבן korban. on day
31. Okay, so here's this very interesting idea that when we say
מקצת היום ככולו, mikzat hayom k'kulo, if something happens in the remainder
of the day then that is fundamentally contradicts what that status was
about, that then actually we say retroactively you never finished and you
have to start the whole thing again. Okay, so that's the principle
that's being taught here, yes.
So the completing moment of is not the shaving or the קרבן,
korban it's nightfall.
Yes, but nightfall in the sense that it retroactively you know well
yes that nightfall in the sense that it's right by bringing... But
you're allowed that's the funny thing, in a way you are you
have stopped being a נזיר, nazir, but if something happens, it makes
us reassess the decision we've made. You know it's like a funny
idea. I'll give you another example. I spoke about during a שחיטה,
Shechitah, cutting the majority of the קנה Kaneh and the majority of
the ושט. Veshet. If I cut just the majority of the trachea
and the esophagus and I stop, the animal will be totally kosher.
But let's say I cut the majority of it and then I
wanted to go the whole way, but in the remainder, that last
what's called the מיעוט אחרון, Miyut Acharon, the remaining minority, I did
something that was פסול. Passul. Okay, I put too much pressure, I
did something that was פסול. Passul. Okay, so it's quite very well
it's a you know there's a Rashi whatever, it's there's a serious
opinion that that invalidates the whole שחיטה. Shechitah. I could have stopped.
You know stop while you're ahead, that's a great example. But no,
I had to go finish it and then I did something wrong.
So then in the end, you know that sort of invalidated the
whole שחיטה. Shechitah. It's not like so here too you can't stop
a day after a קרבן, korban you gotta go live out the
rest of the day. You can't stop the world, right? So if
in that rest of the day something fundamentally wrong happened it retroactively
undermines it. So I wouldn't frame it as you need the end
of the day to finish because you're allowed to go drink wine
after you bring the קרבן korban and get a haircut. It's just
that what happened for the rest of the day could redefine the
beginning of the day. Maybe this makes it better this way: Can
you say the beginning of the day it was a יום טהרה,
Yom Taharah, let's put it that way. If the day ended with
טומאה, Tumah, I can't say that the מקצת Miktzas of the day
in the beginning it was counted as a 30th day בטהרה Be-taharah
because in retrospect that was not a טהור Tahor day. Okay, so
that's sort of the idea here.
So טבול יום Tevul Yom also related to this in a way?
No, even though טבול יום Tevul Yom he has
to wait until the day completes. Yeah, but that is that actually
is different.
A טבול יום Tevul Yom he does not become טהור Tahor until
nightfall. He you know that really... is different. There the end of
the sunset is the completion of the process. Here, no. Your נזירות
nezirut. stopped, you brought your קרבן, korban but we're going to reassess
if something happened afterwards. Okay. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. מי שאמר, Mi she'amar
that was all just the משנה. Mishnah מי שאמר הריני נזיר nazir,
נטמא יום שלושים nitma yom shloshim סותר את הכל.
So it all gets undermined. בשלמא לרב מתנא ניחא, Bishlama leRav Matna
nicha, but according to בר פדא, Bar Padda oh of course it
makes sense! Just like we spent 10 minutes explaining, that's the principle
of מקצת היום miktzat hayom, ככולו, meaning okay, you know, you have
to get your head around it, but you understand the idea. Part
of the day counted as all, you can bring your קרבן, korban.
but if something happened afterwards, we reassess. That all makes sense.
How do you know that the משנה Mishnah means that it's after
you brought the קרבן?
korban, Because then it wouldn't be a חידוש. Because if it's before
you brought the קרבן korban then it could be on day... it
could be on day 31. If you're being late bringing your קרבן,
korban, any time you become טמא, tamei well actually, not necessarily true.
Okay, so it's not explicit. I'm not... I'm going to pull back.
It's not explicit that you brought the קרבן. korban. But we'll... but
we'll assume that for now, okay? Okay. But anyway let's go on.
But you're right, it's not explicit. Okay. Anyway, so it says like
this, אלא לבר פדא קשיא. ela leBar Padda kashya. But according to
בר פדא Bar Padda it's difficult, because according to בר פדא Bar
Padda, day 30 is after, right, you've had a full 29
days. So what is going to make us redefine what
preceded, right? Anything that's happening now is happening after the period of
your נזירות. nezirut Now it is true, because Dov is right, I
jumped ahead, I made it more extreme by saying you brought your
קרבן. korban If you didn't bring your קרבן korban and you became
טמא, tamei let's say I said I'm a normal נזיר nazir day
30 and I've been lazy and it's now day 50 and I
haven't brought my קרבן korban, and I become טמא, tamei what's the
הלכה? halacha Well, I can't bring my קרבן Korban, while I'm טמא.
tamei I have to wait seven days, go through a טהרה tahara
process, and then I'll bring my קרבן after seven days. But it
doesn't redefine the 30 days. The 30 days I completed, that's in
the bank. It's just that now I have to become טהור tahor
before I can bring my קרבן. So the גמרא Gemara is saying,
well that's what would be according to בר פדא. Bar Padda If
you went ahead and on day 30 even if you still haven't
brought your קרבן, okay, because becoming טמא tamei, should not make you
have to do 30 more days. That's... your 29 days are in
the bank. You've done your... you've done your time, okay? All you
would have to do is wait seven days till becoming טהור. tahor.
So how according to בר פדא Bar Padda, should it be that
you would have to do the whole 30 days... the whole 30
days again, which is a really good question. So let's take a
look. אמר לך בר פדא, Amar lach Bar Padda, so בר פדא
Bar Padda will tell you why do you have to do 30
days if you became טמא tamei on day 30? אימא סיפא, Eima
seifa,
look at the end of that משנה. Mishnah רבי אליעזר אומר אינו
סותר אלא שבעה. Rabbi Eliezer omer eino soter ela shiva.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's only going to take... you only
have to do seven days when you become טמא tamei on day
30. So אי סלקא דעתך שלושים בעינן. ei salka daitach shloshim bainan.
Okay, so... period. So meaning, what בר פדא Bar Padda says is
I basically hold like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So now what בר
פדא Bar Padda. we had been until now assuming that he was
using it as a universal explanation, we now find out that he
really is siding with the opinion about רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, okay.
So here, if you've taken a... if you take the whole
60-day thing, which is confusing, okay. Here you are and it's your
day 30, okay.
Now, for בר... so for the חכמים, Chachamim, okay, and it's מקצת
היום, miktzat hayom, okay, and here you become טמא tamei in this
part. So for the חכמים, Chachamim. they... this makes sense that you
really needed 30 days. It was okay to bring your קרבן here,
but in the end, you really needed 30 days. So if you
became טמא tamei here, that retroactively... that טומאה tumah invaded your נזירות.
nezirut. We get that idea according to חכמים. Chachamim. That's... it's based
on מקצת היום, miktzat hayom. okay. That's the חכמים. Chachamim So the
חכמים Chachamim, say another 30 days. But רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
seven. So according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, says בר פדא, Bar
Padda? רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer he's my guy. I would say that
your נזירות nezirut. is 29 days. This is already outside of your
basic נזירות. nezirus. So whatever's going to happen cannot impinge on your
completion of your unit of נזירות. nezirut, Right, but I mean... nothing...
you haven't brought your קרבן, you're still נזיר, nazir, but right, it
doesn't get... it doesn't invade, it doesn't invade your basic... your basic
period of נזירות. nezirut. It's after. So that's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says. It's coming after and therefore you just have to wait
till you become טהור. tahor. It doesn't actually intrude on your נזירות
nezirut itself. So רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer my guy. But you're right,
according to the חכמים, Chachamim. it's pretty clear if you need to
do a whole more 30 days over here, that day 30 is
still part of the main unit of נזירות.
nezirut That if... that's for the חכמים.
Chachamim. Right. And therefore that's what's going on for the חכמים. Chachamim...
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אי... so now it wants
to understand רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer according to רב מתנא, Rav Matna,
right? Because what do you do with רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, according
to רב מתנא? Rav Matna? Why? So אי סלקא דעתך שלושים בעינן,
ei salka daitach shloshim bainan, one minute. According to רב מתנא, Rav
Matna, as this is how תוספות reads it, according to רב מתנא,
Rav Matna, if you need 30 days and if that's true even
for רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer. ניסתרו כולהו. nistaru kulhu. So now חכמים...
now רב מתנא Rav Matna you explain
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer Right, בר פדא Bar Padda said I
can see the
חכמים... days, shouldn't you have to do the whole thing again if
you became טמא tamei *tamei* on day 30? So רב מתנא *Rav
Masna* said: No, כסבר רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, *Kasavar Rebbe Eliezer* מקצת
היום miktzat hayom ככולו *miktzas hayom kekulo*. He holds מקצת היום miktzat
hayom ככולו *miktzas hayom kekulo*. Now the question is, what do you
mean? Until now everybody held מקצת היום miktzat hayom ככולו *miktzas hayom
kekulo*. That's why you're bringing your קרבנות Korbanos, *korbonos*. But the point
is, he holds like a real מקצת היום miktzat hayom ככולו *miktzas
hayom kekulo*, meaning like no, when part of your day is over,
you are done. You don't look at the rest of the day.
Okay, so what the חכמים *chachamim* say, what רב מתנא *Rav Masna*
says the debate of the חכמים *chachamim* and רבי אליעזר *Rebbe Eliezer*
is, is that everybody says you need day thirty. The question is,
for the חכמים *chachamim*, when the beginning enters in, you're okay, but
the rest of the day still matters. And if something happens, we're
going to reassess. And for רבי אליעזר *Rebbe Eliezer*, he has like
this iron wall come down. You're done the beginning of the day,
the rest is completely irrelevant. So it's a different, it's a more
vigorous, you know, מקצת היום miktzat hayom, ככולו *miktzas hayom kekulo*.
It's a מחלוקת machloket *machlokes* on how to conceptualize that.
How to conceptualize מקצת היום ככולו *miktzas hayom kekulo*. Right. So whereas
בר פדא Bar Padda, *Bar Pada* says רבי אליעזר *Rebbe Eliezer* says
you're done at day 29, and that's the debate, 29 days or
30 days, and that's why they debate what happens when you become
טמא tamei *tamei*. Okay, the חכמים *chachamim* say everybody says 30 days,
the question is how you look at מקצת היום *miktzas hayom*. Does
that still leave it open-ended till the end and we're going to
reassess, or does it completely end with מקצת היום *miktzas hayom*? Yes.
Does the גמרא Gemara *gemara* often see it where it assumes that
רב מתנא *Rav Masna* must be able to be understandable by both
sides?
Yes, the גמרא Gemara *gemara*, right, so the גמרא Gemara *gemara* often,
because if you're an אמורא *amora*, you want to have everybody go
like you. Right, so if you don't have any choice, you have
to say okay, I'm siding with one תנא *tanna*, I concede. But
the stronger position is my position works according to everyone. Right? So
yes, if forced to, the גמרא Gemara *gemara* would say that. But
the point is we're not forced to say it, right? Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says like this:
תנן *Tnan*. Now we're going to have another interesting משנה Mishnah. *mishna*
which רבי אליעזר *Rebbe Eliezer* gets to touches on David's point. הריני
נזיר nazir מאה יום *Hareini nazir meiah yom*. A person says a
hundred days. Okay now, a person says explicitly a hundred days, there's
no 29 for בר פדא Bar Padda *Bar Pada*. Keep that in
mind. For בר פדא Bar Padda *Bar Pada*, he doesn't hold of
מקצת היום ככולו *miktzas hayom kekulo*. So for בר פדא *Bar Pada*,
if a guy said a hundred days, when would he have to
bring his קרבן *korban*? On day 101, right? Because he doesn't hold
of מקצת היום *miktzas hayom*. But the only חידוש *chiddush* of בר
פדא *Bar Pada* is that סתם *stam*, I'm a נזיר nazir, *nazir*,
means 29. But if you explicitly mention the number, you have to
bring it on the following day because he doesn't hold of מקצת
היום *miktzas hayom*. Yeah, Jenna.
Can בר פדא *Bar Pada* do that where he uses רבי אליעזר
*Rebbe Eliezer* in one situation but disagrees with him in another?
No, so what he would claim, well okay, so what he would
probably claim, the simplest thing to say is he would say when
going back to all those earlier things, you know, I would say
that those are going according to רבי אליעזר *Rebbe Eliezer*. Or I'm
a...
but if רבי אליעזר *Rebbe Eliezer* holds of מקצת היום ככולו *miktzas
hayom kekulo*, then it's not going according to רבי אליעזר *Rebbe Eliezer*
fully, right?
Wait, one more time.
רבי אליעזר *Rebbe Eliezer* holds מקצת היום ככולו *miktzas hayom kekulo*.
Right. And how does...
no, no, רבי אליעזר *Rebbe Eliezer* holds מקצת היום ככולו *miktzas hayom
kekulo* only according to the חכמים *chachamim*. Right? I mean, only according
to רב מתנא *Rav Masna*. Meaning רב מתנא *Rav Masna* says they
both, you got it?
So בר פדא *Bar Pada* would say רבי
אליעזר *Rebbe Eliezer*'s position is my position. No מקצת היום *miktzas hayom*,
yes 29 days. Okay, is that clear?
So they're just using each other consistently.
Exactly, exactly. Is that clear everybody? Right? חכמים *Chachamim* say these guys
both go like me. Anyway, 30 days, and they're debating what, whether
מקצת היום *miktzas hayom* is complete or not. And בר פדא *Bar
Pada* says I gotta concede the חכמים *chachamim*'s position, but רבי אליעזר
*Rebbe Eliezer*, he's my guy. 29 days, no מקצת היום *miktzas hayom*.
And that's what, why he's saying it's not a big deal if
you become טמא tamei *tamei* on day 30. Okay? So good, so
let's take a look now. תנן *Tnan*, but now it's going to
throw it into a question because now we're still saying רבי אליעזר
*Rebbe Eliezer* with בר פדא *Bar Pada* and רבי אליעזר *Rebbe Eliezer*
don't hold of מקצת היום *miktzas hayom*. So let's see what happens
if you say a hundred days. You're explicit about the duration. תנן
*Tnan*, הריני נזיר nazir, מאה יום *Hareini nazir meiah yom*. I'm a
נזיר nazir *nazir* for a hundred days. נטמא יום מאה *Nitma yom
meiah*. On day 100 you're still... okay, סותר הכל *soiser hakol*. It
all gets undermined. That's the principle of מקצת היום ככולו *miktzas hayom
kekulo*. Right, it's later in the day, so maybe you could have
brought your קרבן *korban*. Okay, either it holds one of two things.
Okay, let's redo this. So now
we've got a person explicitly said a hundred days. Okay, and here's
day 100. Now everybody agrees, he said a hundred days, there's no
day 99 here. Okay, so if you're נטמא *nitma*, it's סותר הכל
*soiser hakol*. נטמא *nitma* is סותר הכל *soiser hakol*, everything. You have
to do another hundred. Okay, you gotta do another hundred. Now,
what does that demonstrate? Well, one of two things: either you hold
מקצת היום *miktzas hayom*, but you look at the end of the
day, or what's the other possibility? Why would you have to do
it all again? One possibility is you hold מקצת היום, but the
rest of the day still matters. What's the other possibility? You don't
hold מקצת היום. Okay, so this works whether Bar Padda or Rav
Masna, right? We're still good with that idea. Okay, because either you
don't hold מקצת היום or you held it, but you had to
look at the end of the day. Now it goes on. רבי
אליעזר אומר אינו סותר אלא שלשים יום.
Rabbi Eliezer
omer
ein soter ela sheloshim yom. So now this is Rabbi Eliezer is
very strange, okay? Because like, first of all, make up your mind,
right? Either, which is what the גמרא's Gemara. gonna say, either you
hold מקצת היום and this iron wall and after, right, which is
what the שיטת רבי אליעזר shitat Rabbi Eliezer and afterwards is immaterial,
so you would only have to do seven days in terms of
the way this is coming to
us, not thirty.
Or Bar Padda, you don't hold מקצת היום at all according to
Rabbi Eliezer and you would have to do 100 days. So would
you please make up your mind, does Rabbi Eliezer work according to
either explanation that we've given before? Everybody with me?
Yeah, what's Rabbi Eliezer's original statement?
Here it is, you need thirty. In his previous one, he said
you needed seven.
Right. When was, when was it thirty days? Rabbi Eliezer said you
needed seven. How did we explain that? We either explained it meant
מקצת היום ככולה miktzat hayom k'kula complete, right, ממש, mamash, full. Okay,
so this is like you know, like that. It's completely unrelated and
therefore it's outside. Or it meant 29 days, that סתם נזירות nezirut.
is 29 days. So one way or the other, when you became
טמא, you were in a different zone. That was the previous Rabbi
Eliezer. But this Rabbi Eliezer doesn't make any sense. If he held
the idea 29 days, that's anyway completely irrelevant. He doesn't hold of
מקצת היום and you should have to do the whole 100. And
if he held that this wall came down, then you should only
have to do seven. Where are you getting this idea of thirty?
Which is a question regardless. How does Rabbi Eliezer jump from seven
here to thirty here? Okay, so let's take a look at what
the גמרא Gemara says.
ואי סלקא דעתך סבר רבי אליעזר מקצת היום ככולה, v'isalka da'atach savar
Rabbi Eliezer miktzat hayom k'kula, if it was like Rav
Masna that it's מקצת היום ככולה, miktzat hayom k'kula, a full מקצת
היום ככולה miktzat hayom k'kula and anything later is completely
irrelevant, וליסתור שבעה, v'listar shiva, it should only be a week because
you're completely out of your 100 days.
ואי לא סבר מקצת היום ככולה, v'iy lo savar miktzat hayom k'kula,
if he's like Bar Padda and holds that there's no such thing
as מקצת היום ככולה, miktzat hayom k'kula, right, all he had was
some idea about 29 days, it's irrelevant here, he held of no
מקצת היום ככולה, miktzat hayom k'kula, then וליסתור כולו, v'listar kulo, you
should have to do the whole 100 days again. So how do
you explain this weird idea of thirty days? Very good question. Let's
see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. אמר ריש לקיש היינו טעמא
דרבי אליעזר. amar Reish Lakish hainu ta'ama d'Rabbi Eliezer. Here's his reasoning.
Did I skip a line? Yeah. אי הכי
ואי לא סבר מקצת היום ככולה וליסתור כולו. iy hachi v'iy lo
savar miktzat hayom k'kula v'listar kulo. לעולם לא אמרינן מקצת היום ככולה.
l'olam lo amrinan miktzat hayom k'kula. So we're going to answer it
according to Bar Padda. תוספות worries how you're going to answer it
to Rav Masna, but we're confused enough so we're just going to
focus on what the גמרא Gemara says. Here's how we're going to
answer it according to Bar Padda. He doesn't hold of מקצת היום
ככולה. miktzat hayom k'kula. Okay, so if he doesn't hold of it,
you should have to do the whole 100 days again. No.
ואי לא סבר ככולה אי הכי וליסתור כולו, v'iy lo savar k'kula
iy hachi v'listar kulo, אמר ריש לקיש היינו טעמא דרבי אליעזר. amar
Reish Lakish hainu ta'ama d'Rabbi Eliezer. Here's his reasoning. אמר קרא זאת
תהיה תורת
הנזיר ביום מלאת ימי נזרו.
amar kra: zot tihiyeh
torat
ha-Nazir b'yom melot yemei nizro. This will be the law of the
נזיר Nazir on the day that is completed the days of his
נזירות. neziroot. התורה אמרה, ha-Torah amrah, so the תורה's Torah saying נטמא
ביום מלאת, nitma b'yom melot, the יום מלאת yom melot is the
day that it's completed. If you get טמא on the final day,
נטמא ביום מלאת תן לו תורת נזיר. nitma b'yom melot ten lo
torat nazir. So what is the תורת נזיר? torat nazir? The תורת
נזיר torat nazir is standard נזירות. neziroot So there's a special הלכה
halacha. that if you get טמא on the last day, we're not
going to make you do the whole thing again. If it was
a longer נזירות, neziroot. all you have to do is a standard
נזירות. neziroot So here's what it says. So in this scenario, why
do I only have to do seven days according to Bar Padda?
Didn't he become טמא on the last day? Here's a trick question.
See if you're paying attention. Why? Because what was the last day?
29,
excellent, you all passed. Okay, so this was the day after the
last day. So no problem, just become טהור tahor and bring your
קרבן. But when you became טמא on day 100 or if you
became טמא on day 29, then you'd have to do a whole
other נזירות nezirot thirty days or 29 according to Bar Padda. But
okay, it's a special הלכה. halacha If it's your last day, it's
not מקצת היום,
and the תורה Torah is going easy on you. If you became
טמא on your very last day, you only have to do a
standard נזירות nezirot again. You don't have to do your entire נזירות.
nezirot But the interesting thing about ריש לקיש Reish Lakish here is
that he concedes there's no logic—it's a logical problem. Yeah. So let's
go back to the תורה Torah to see the hermeneutic. Let's read
the תורה Torah differently. Exactly.
Yeah, because how do you go from saying I'm here on the
last day of seven and here on the last day is thirty?
There's no logic. You have to come up with a new rule.
Okay, so now that we've said very nicely explanation of רבי אליעזר
within בר פדא, does not hold of מקצת היום ככולו, holds of
a special הלכה Halacha, becoming טמא on the last day.
Okay,
לימא כתנאי, Leima kitnai, let's say the debate of of רב מסנא
Rav Masna and בר פדא is like the following debate of תנאים.
tannaim. עד מלאות הימים, Ad melot hayamim, until the full of the
days, like what is it, עד מלאות הימים אשר יזיר לה' את
ימי נזרו קדוש יהיה גדל פרע שער ראשו, Ad melot hayamim asher
yazir l'Adonai et yemei nizro kadosh yihye gadel pera sear rosho, I
think that's the פסוק. pasuk. Okay, until the full of the days.
שמעני מיעוט ימים שנים, Shimani miut yamim shnayim, this is a ברייתא.
braita. מה אני מקיים עד מלאות הימים, Ma ani mekayem ad melot
hayamim, so that's true, days is two. No, תלמוד לומר קדוש יהיה
גדל פרע, Talmud lomar kadosh yihye gadel pera, is holy will be
the growing of the wildness of the hair. אין גידול פרע שער
פחות משלושים. Ein gidul pera sear pachot mishloshim. That's no less than
thirty days. דברי רבי יאשיה. Divrei Rabbi Yoshiya. That's what רבי יאשיה
Rabbi Yoshiya says. רבי יונתן אומר, Rabbi Yonatan omer, אינו צריך, eino
tzarich, you don't need to learn it out from there. הרי הוא
אומר, Harei hu omer, עד מלאות הימים, ad melot hayamim, until the
full of the days. אי אלו הן הימים שצריכין למלאות, Ei elu
hen hayamim shetzrichin l'malot, what are days that need to be filled?
הוי אומר שלושים, Hevei omer shloshim, thirty. What does that mean? It
means that there's an idea of a month, and a month sometimes
has 29 days and sometimes has 30 days. Is it a full
month or not a full month? But there's an idea of filling
out an amount and that comes, it can't come with a week.
You can't say a full week or not a full week, a
week is seven days.
Okay, so therefore, but you could say a full month or not
a full month, so an idea of a fill of days only
makes sense thinking in terms of a month. Okay, that's nice, different
דרשות. drashot. One focuses on the idea of a fill of days
and the other that if it's about the hair, the minimum amount
that you can say hair is growing wild is thirty days. But
what the גמרא Gemara does is it wants to turn this into
the debate of בר פדא and רב מסנא Rav Masna and saying
the first opinion, even though it mentioned hair, it really wasn't about
the hair, because it had that magic word in the first approach
which was
גדל יהיה, gadel yihye, you know, קדוש יהיה גדל פרע שער ראשו.
kadosh yihye gadel pera sear rosho. The יהיה, yihye, remember, that's the
גימטריא gematria of thirty. So it wants to make... you forgot that.
So it wants to make the first opinion רב מסנא Rav Masna
because it quoted the פסוק pasuk of יהיה, yihye, and the second
opinion בר פדא. How is the second opinion בר פדא? Because if
he's talking about a full month and a non-full month, then you
could say it means the non-full month, right? So and that's... so
the focusing on a month that's full or not full, maybe he
means the non-full version and that's twenty-nine. So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara's says. מאי לאו רב מסנא דאמר כרבי יאשיה? Mai lav
Rav Masna d'amar k'Rabbi Yoshiya? Is it not that רב מסנא Rav
Masna is like רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya and we'll say that רבי
יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya is quoting the פסוק pasuk of קדוש יהיה kadosh
yihye is to get you to the גימטריא gematria of thirty of
the יהיה. yihye. ובר פדא דאמר כרבי יונתן? U'Var Padda d'amar k'Rabbi
Yonatan? And בר פדא would say like רבי יונתן. Rabbi Yonatan. And
when he would say the fill of the days, now of course
you're used to be saying to me, but what do you mean?
It says the full of the days, so you should of course
mean the full month, thirty. How do you get twenty-nine? So no,
what he would say it means is the keyword is עד, ad,
until. So there's the classic question of does עד ad mean inclusive
or not inclusive? Until and including or include and up to but
not including? So he would have said when it says until the
fill of the days, until day thirty means but not including day
thirty. Okay, so therefore one has the קדוש יהיה kadosh yihye thirty
days, and the other is until the full fill, but not including
the full, so only twenty-nine days. Okay, מאי... mai... so we said
that. אמר לך רב מסנא, Amar lach Rav Masna, so רב מסנא
Rav Masna would say, כולי
עלמא שלושים בעינן. kulei alma shloshim bayinan. Everybody says no, no, no,
and here's exactly the point about like I'd rather have everybody go
like me. Okay, so he'd say look, I would say everybody says
that you need
thirty. So what's the יהיה yihye versus עד מלאות? ad melot? So
he says והכא בעד ועד בכלל פליגי. v'hacha b'ad v'ad bichlal pligi.
The question: רבי יאשיה סבר עד ולא עד בכלל, Rabbi Yoshiya savar
ad v'lo ad bichlal, when it says until it means until but
not including. רבי יונתן סבר עד ועד בכלל, Rabbi Yonatan savar ad
v'ad bichlal, until and including. So one says it means so I
mean one isn't even looking at the פסוק pasuk of עד מלאות.
ad melot. But the point is קדוש יהיה kadosh yihye works for
me because the יהיה yihye is thirty, and עד מלאות ad melot
also works for me because עד מלאות ad melot I would say
doesn't mean up to but not including, I'd say עד מלאות ad
melot means up to and including, so and including the מלאות melot
is thirty days. So I can get both of them to work
for me. Okay, and implicitly בר פדא, it's not spelled out, would
have to concede well, I can get the second opinion to work
for me because up to can mean up to and not including,
but the first position I gotta concede doesn't work like me. Okay,
so it doesn't spell out that second half, but that's anyway what
we've seen according to בר פדא that בר פדא has to concede
I'm not going like everyone. I'm going only like רבי אליעזר, maybe
I'm only
going... But רב מתנא is saying, no, no, I'm gonna get everybody
to work like me. Even עד מלאות ad milos means עד ad
and including, up to and including, and therefore it's 30 days. Okay,
now the גמרא's Gemara going to look at how we got this
דרשה. drasha. אמר מר: Amar Mar: אי אלו הן ימים שצריכים למלאות?
הוי אומר שלשים. I eilei hen yamim shetzrichim lemalo? Hevei omer shloshim.
30, 30 that can be a fill of 30 or not a
fill. ואימא שבת? Ve'eima shabbos? How about שבת? shabbos? That's also a
unit that gets filled, a full seven days. No, שבת מי איכא
חסירותא? shabbos mi ika chasirootah? You can't talk about it being full
if it's never empty. Okay, you never have a week that's not
full. Okay, now you could say you have all seven days, but
nevertheless it understands a fill of it suggests that there could be
smaller versions of it and larger versions of it. So then only
works within the concept of a month. ואימא שנה? Ve'eima shana? How
about a year? There could be a year, a year could have,
you know, a Hebrew year could be 354 days, it could be
384 days or 83 days if it's a leap year, right? It
could be, you know, it could be different sizes. Some of the
months could be חסר, chaser, some could be מלא, malei, it swings,
and you could add a month and not add a month. So
maybe it means, it means a full year. No, מי מנינן לימי?
mi maninan leyamin? No, no, no, because you don't count a year
according to days. It says מלאת הימים, milot hayamim, and a year
is counted by the number of months. Okay, it's true there is
a duration of days to a year, but it's not the unit
of counting. והא רבנן דקיסרי אמרי, Veha Rabbanan d'Kisari amri, and the
Rabbis of Caesarea say: מנין שאין מונין ימים לשנים? Minayin she'ein monin
yamin leshanim? How do you know you don't count days for a
year? That it's not in הלכה, Halacha, it's sort of not the
unit of counting. You count months and not days. שנאמר: לחדשי השנה.
Shene'emar: lechodeshei hashana. For the months of the year. חדשים מחשבינן לשנים
ולא ימים לשנים. Chodashim mechashvinan leshanim velo yamin leshanim.
We count months towards a year and not days towards a year.
And that's relevant in different areas of הלכה, right? Exactly this, like
do we say well it wasn't a full year because it wasn't
365 days, you know, or do we mean like think about how
we talk about it. If it's January 6th, and you say until
the same time next year, we don't start figuring out whether it
was a leap year, whether it was 365 days or 366 days,
right? Means that you go by the, you know, the month, the
month and the day or whatever, but not by the number of
days. So here too you go by the number of months, so
מלאת הימים milot hayamim has to be some type of a unit
that is counted by days that can have a shorter and a
longer version. And the only candidate there is the idea of a
month.
Anything to say about this רבנן דקיסרי? Rabbanan d'Kisari? It's just Rabbi
חנינא, Chanina, isn't it?
Yeah, I don't know. חנינא? Chanina? Okay. I mean, they do come
up interestingly and I think the גמרא Gemara in beginning of עירובין
Eruvin and whatever, about being interested in sort of more mathematical things
actually.
Well that is interesting. It was a pagan city. Oh really? Tremendous
amount of general culture.
Oh really? Because they have a very interesting opinion about some of
these גמרות Gemaros about the geometry and about figuring out the relative
size of a circle inscribed in a square and a square inscribed
in a circle. So there is actually, so that might be related.
Okay, so let's try to get a little further, why not, as
I've been told that יום כפור's Yom Kippur coming up. I'm not
going to be for שבת, Shabbos, but Dan Margulies is going to
give the דף, and he's had
great reviews last time he gave it, so yeah, so that'll be
fun. All right, so the משנה Mishnah
says like this: אמר הריני נזיר אחת גדולה, הריני נזיר אחת קטנה.
Amar Hareini nazir achat gedola, Hareini nazir achat ketana. So somebody says,
behold I'm a נזיר, Nazir, a single נזיר, Nazir a big single
נזיר, Nazir, or I'm going to be a small but only I'll
be one נזירות. nezirot. Okay, I'll be one, I'm accepting upon myself
one big נזירות nezirus or one small נזירות. nezirus אפילו מכאן עד
סוף העולם, Afilu mikan ad sof ha'olam, or even if he says
I'm accepting on myself a נזירות nezirus, from now till the end
of the world. נזר שלשים יום. Nazar shloshim yom. He is a
נזיר Nazir for 30 days.
So which basically means that nice sort of
illustration, exactly, a nice illustration of סתם נזירות שלשים יום. stam neziroot
shloshim yom. Now, of course, what does big and small mean? So
you could say look, big and small, you're not telling me how
big, right? So it's, so therefore I'm just, you said you're a
נזיר, Nazir, that means 30 days. If you give me a different
number, I'll take a different number. If you don't give me a
different number, then all I know is a נזיר Nazir 30 days.
Big, who knows what big means? Big means it's a big deal
for you. I don't know what big means.
Okay, I'm going to say that this נזיר, Nazir
you're going to have the biggest head of hair. I don't know
what big means, but it does, but you said נזיר, Nazir you
didn't tell me any other number, that's what it means. The question
is what about when he says from now until the end of
the world, מכאן עד סוף העולם? mikan ad sof ha'olam? That should
translate into a duration, right? Now on the one hand, though, he
is talking about, about, you know, measuring distance and נזיר Nazir does
a measure of days, right? Right? He doesn't say from now till
the end of time. I mean, I guess you could say עד
סוף העולם ad sof ha'olam means the end of time, like, you
know, but it sounds like מכאן, mikan, from here, sounds like it's
talking about a measuring of a distance. would maybe doesn't directly translate
into time. So that's the question: why don't we say that though
means from now until
infinitum? If I said from now, maybe we would say it means
נזיר עולם, Nazir Olam, but from here until the other end of
the world, from here to China. Okay, I'm a נזיר Nazir from
here to China. What does that mean? Does that mean you're a
נזיר עולם? Nazir Olam? I mean, how do we take distance and
translate into time? So the משנה Mishnah. says we don't. The משנה
Mishnah. says, no, you said you're a נזיר, Nazir you didn't give
us a different time, so a נזיר Nazir is thirty days. Okay,
let's see what the גמרא says.
Oh, wait, so the word עולם Olam here does not mean like
לעולמי עד le'olamei ad temporal this locative
it is- it's very much- exactly. So if you say from here
to China, I'm a נזיר, Nazir you're a נזיר Nazir for thirty
days. Okay, let's take a look. אמאי, Amai, from here to Pluto,
I'm a נזיר, nazir all right? So you're a נזיר nazir for
thirty days.
אמאי ומכאן ועד סוף העולם כמה? Amai u'mikan ve'ad sof ha'olam kama?
The גמרא is not bothered by the earlier cases. It says small,
big, fine, we don't know what that means, but this actually seems
to say like for forever, or it's something that should be translated
in that way, of meaning like forever. So the גמרא says, no,
הכי קאמר: Hachi ka'amar: אריכא לי הדא מילתא כמכאן ועד סוף העולם.
aricha li hada milta kemikan ve'ad sof ha'olam. This נזירות nezirus is
gonna be such a big pain for me, so it's gonna feel
so long it'll be like from here to China. But again, if
you told us time, it would change what the נזירות nezirus. was,
but you didn't tell us time. You told us distance. So where
does it say that's gonna be a big deal for you? We're
not gonna translate it in other ways. Okay. So תנן: הריני
נזיר מכאן ועד
מקום פלוני.
Hareini nazir mikan ve'ad
makom ploni. I'm a נזיר nazir from here until this place. אומרים:
Omrim: could you- I'm sorry, I'm
sorry, I'm gonna have to ask you guys- I'm gonna have to
ask you guys. No, no, no, you have to leave, you have
to leave.
Sorry.
Eddie, Eddie, you gotta- you gotta go. Okay. Okay,
אמר
תנן: Amar tnan: הריני נזיר מכאן ועד מקום פלוני. Hareini nazir mikan
ve'ad makom ploni. If somebody says I'm a נזיר nazir from here
until such and such a place. I'm a נזיר nazir from here
until Atlanta. אומרים: Omrim: כמה ימים מכאן ועד מקום פלוני? Kama yamim
mikan ve'ad makom ploni? How many days does it take to get
from here to that place? I don't know, walking, on horseback, I
guess based on how normally people would travel. Okay, but you figure
out what the normal, what's considered to be the normal duration. פחות
משלושים יום נזיר Pachot mishloshim yom nazir thirty days. So if the
normal travel time would be less than thirty days, נזיר שלושים יום.
nazir shloshim yom. So you can't accept a נזירות nezirus, less than
thirty days, so you're a נזיר nazir for thirty days. ואם לאו
נזיר כמניין הימים. Ve'im lav nazir keminyan hayamim. But if not, you're
a נזיר nazir for the actual number of days that that travel
takes. So this ברייתא braita seems very different from the משנה. You
could be talking about distance and even though you're talking about distance,
we translate that into travel time and we say you take that
travel time and that defines the duration of your נזירות. nezirus So
if you ask me, maybe it's just a מחלוקת המשנה והברייתא. hamishnah
ve'habraita. The ברייתא braita is prepared to say when you describe distance
we translate that into time and the משנה says we're not prepared
to say that. But the גמרא is gonna try to reconcile it.
So let's see the גמרא. Okay, so the גמרא says like this:
ואימא הכא נמי אריכא לי המילתא כמכאן ועד מקום פלוני. Ve'eima hacha
nami aricha li hamilta kemikan ve'ad makom ploni. Let me say here
too that basically if you're describing distance, it just means it's such
a שלעפ shlep for me. It's gonna be such a שלעפ shlep
like going all the way to Chicago. Okay, maybe that's what you
mean and maybe don't translate into time. So אמר רבא: Amar Rava:
שהחזיק
בדרך. Shehechzik baderech. No, we'd be talking about a scenario in the
ברייתא braita that you're already on the journey. You're already in the
car, that solves the problem of how do we know which type
of mode of transportation you're talking about. You've already started your journey,
you're in the car and you're saying I'm a נזיר from here
till Chicago. Well, if you're driving to Chicago, then obviously that translates
into until I get to Chicago, right? Until for the duration of
this journey. Makes a lot of sense, right? If you're in the
middle of the journey and you say from here until there, it
means from here until I get there, which is an amount of
time. But if you're sitting at your home and you're saying I'm
a נזיר from here to Chicago,
why should I say that means
time? That's just some expression that you're using. You understand, it doesn't
make a lot of sense. If you're on the journey, you're thinking
about from here till there means, right, it's always very interesting, right,
when you're like driving on the highway, oh you know when you're
on Google or whatever, oh, oh, this is the different, Google will
tell you, one of these apps will tell you how many miles
you have to get there, and the other will say in ten
minutes take a right, of in ten minutes. How much miles? Right?
But once you're driving, you're starting also measuring distance by time. How
long is it going to take me to get there, right? So
if you're on the road when you say until here, it means
that's the length of time. תוספות also adds a nice point, which
is maybe also you're afraid of the journey and therefore it's sort
of like there's one of these like little deals with God, like
I'll be a נזיר until I get there, so that you'll protect
me on my journey. Okay, that's interesting. I don't know if you
need to say that
psych- So now the גמרא says like this: וליהוי
כל פרסה ופרסה. ve-lehve kol parsa u-parsa. Why don't we say, now
there's a question whether to read this in רבא's Rava case or
back in the משנה. תוספות reads this back in the משנה. So
when you say from here till the end of the world, why
don't we say what it means is count the amount? So your
whole problem was you can't translate distance into time if you're not
on the journey itself. Fine, but let's talk about distance. You're here
and you say from here to the end of the world. From
here to the end of the world is a thousand miles. So
a thousand miles doesn't equal time, but at least you have the
number a thousand. So maybe what we should say that means is
you're accepting upon yourself a thousand נזירות's. nezirus Got it? If you're
on the journey, distance means time. Distance is translated into how long
it's going to take me to get there. If you're not on
the journey, you just have a number. From here to China. Fine,
but let's say that number is a thousand miles, and therefore you're
saying from here, I'm a נזיר a thousand. What does a נזיר
a thousand mean without a time unit? Maybe it means a thousand
נזירות's. nezirus Okay, so why don't we say וליהוי כל פרסה ופרסה?
ve-lehve kol parsa u-parsa? אמר רב פפא: Amar Rav Pappa: באתרא דלא
מנו פרסי. be-atra de-lo manu parsei.
Yeah, they don't measure by miles. Okay, you know, yeah, you gotta
get the number first. How do you know from here to China?
Are you measuring it in miles? Are you measuring it in inches?
What are you measuring it in? Well, they don't measure in miles,
so you can't assume a given number emerges. When you say from
here to there, well what number are you talking about? What do
you mean what number? Depends what measurement I'm using, right? So you
can't get to a number. So אמר רב... Amar Rav... so he
says באתרא דלא מנו פרסי. be-atra de-lo manu parsei. וליהוי כל אבנא
ואבנא. ve-lehve kol avna ve-avna. Let it go by like every, you
know, every stop, which I don't really get what that means, still
like, you know, how would that translate into a number? But how
do they translate the word אבנא avna there in the, I'm curious.
Each and every lodging.
Lodging. Okay. So let it go by every lodging. Again, I don't
still why that necessarily translates into a number, but presumably what it
might mean is, you know, again, let's figure out the number of
days, but we were just saying you can't translate like distance into
days. Anyway, it's still asking some version of the same question.
How do you make this days?
What? Every night, I mean that's
basically saying days, at every night's lodging, so then maybe there's, like,
I feel like there's more of a connection then than we were
talking about a day.
Right. Right, but again like why we sort of say that when
you're not on the journey you don't translate it into duration, because
here we're still working in this mode of let's assume fine, it
doesn't mean duration, but somehow means a number. And like, so I
guess that's the point, like if it's in your mind like a
five-day journey, so say from here to there, the number five dominates,
so even if it's not a five-day נזירות, nezirus somehow we're in
the mode now where we're saying let it be the number of
נזירות's nezirus you're accepting upon yourself. Okay, that's somehow the question. If
you're on the journey and you say from here to there, it
means this is the duration of my נזירות. nezirus If you're not
on the journey and you say I'm a נזיר X, what it
could mean is not the duration of your נזירות, nezirus but X
number of נזירות's nezirus. you're accepting. So somehow now, I don't know,
because we're saying, well, let's say that we can get a number
out of there. How do you measure? I don't know, you measure,
let's measure it by number, by lodgings. Each period of נזירות nezirus
ends at when you lodge and then...
No, no, no, no, no, no. Any... No, so even if you
were measuring by miles, and each mile takes you 10 minutes or
20 minutes to walk or whatever it is, if you accepted a
hundred... if you said a hundred miles and we would have translated
that as a hundred נזירות's, Nezirus that would be a hundred units
of 30 days. It would be a hundred months. That's gonna be
pretty heavy. Okay, but fine, I get that you can't translate distance
into time, but let's say distance, out of the distance idea emerges
a number, and that number means that's the number of different 30-day
נזירות's neziruses, you've accepted upon yourself.
So this just sounds like a יד Yad discussion maybe.
Okay, but let's see anyway what it says. Okay, מי לא תנן,
mi lo tnan, did we not teach, הריני נזיר כעפר הארץ, hareini
nazir ke-afar ha-aretz, I am a נזיר like the dust of the
earth. וכשער ראשי, u-ki-sear roshi, and the hairs on my head. וכחול
הים, u-ke-chol ha-yam, the sand on the sea. הרי זה נזיר עולם,
harei ze nazir olam, he is a נזיר עולם nazir olam forever.
ומגלח אחד לשלושים יום, u-megaleach echad le-shloshim yom, every 30 days. What
does it mean? Because actually this is... there's
a difference between being a נזיר עולם, nazir olam, a נזיר of
eternal duration, and a... you're gonna be a נזיר your whole life
because you've now accepted upon yourself 10,000 נזירות's neziruses. and after each
one ends, the next one will begin. Okay, so in practice you'll
be a נזיר for your whole life, but conceptually you have 10,000
נזירות's nezirus. you have to satisfy. So at the end of every
30 days, you'll bring a קרבן and you'll start your next נזירות
neziruses. and then you'll bring a קרבן and you'll start your next
נזירות. I don't know, if I was in that situation, I just
wouldn't bring a קרבן, so then my next נזירות would never start,
so I wouldn't have to be bringing a... if I was in
that situation, I just wouldn't bring a קרבן, so then my next
נזירות would never start. So I wouldn't have to be bringing all
these קרבנות, you know? But anyway, but maybe that would be considered
not fulfilling my vow, and tell you what, I'm not going to
fulfill my vow anyway, because I'm not going to bring the number
of hairs on my head, I'm never going to get to that
number. Okay, but that's what it basically says. That's different than נזיר
עולם, Nazir Olam, which is the duration is forever, zero is just
for forever. So the question of the גמרא and we really have
to end, the question of the גמרא is, well, here we go
by the number, and we translate the number of hairs on your
head to the number of נזירות, why don't we go by a
number when you say from here to China? So the גמרא's answer
is, and I don't really understand the answer, so we'll leave with
this very satisfying answer or otherwise is, the גמרא says like this,
כל מילתא דאית בה קציצותא לא קתני. Kol milta d'is bei ketzisusa
lo k'tani. If it has a fixed number, we didn't say it.
So somehow it's saying that the sands of the sea, hairs on
the head maybe has a number, sands on the sea nobody thinks
that they can count, right? It's just and saying from here to
China there is a more concrete number that we can come out
with, whatever unit we're measuring in. So somehow ironically when I say
something that doesn't have a concrete number like sand on the sea,
I mean an infinite number of sequential נזירות. Okay, when I say
something that a concrete number could emerge, from here to China, but
maybe I don't know what that concrete number is, what's my way
of measuring it, then I'm just speaking like then I'm just exaggerating,
then we don't really have a number and I really mean one
נזירות.
Because it was said China's not so far man.
I know. So I was changing, but תוספות says and the ראשונים
Rishonim say that the גמרא says elsewhere that the distance of the
circumference of the world is five hundred פרסאות parsa'ot so it does
have a number for that. Okay, so somehow again when I say
something without a time duration, even if I say big, small, to
the end of the world, if I don't have a clear number
and I don't have a clear time duration, I mean one. If
I'm on a journey and I say until we get there, then
in that context that means a certain amount of time, that makes
a lot of sense. And if I say something that has a
number but a number that's completely not determined, sand on the sea,
somehow for some reason that case actually we say means an infinite
number of sequential נזירות. So I will let Dan Margulies finish this
very complicated discussion tomorrow.